People can often wonder:
how can a personal trainer with an online
coaching app
become a Sunday Times number one
bestselling author three times?
Well, it's the exact same way
that I've had over 120,000 people use my
coaching
app over the last nine years.
The big problem that there is online with
other gurus talking in this niche is,
first of all,
they've never had a big fitness
business, and two,
they're kind of just regurgitating what
other people are saying
online that have never run an online
fitness business.
So in this video,
I'm going to condense all of the things
that I've done wrong and
right in the last 10 years so you can save
yourself so much time, energy,
effort, confusion, and do the thing
that you want to, which
is be a great coach,
work online,
have a tight cohort of clients
that love you for what you do, and be
able to generate a few thousand dollars a
month by opening your laptop.
There's going to be 20 lessons,
and as we go through each
and every lesson, there's
going to be a link in the description
saying, called the PT Starter Kit.
It's a product that I designed for
personal trainers.
Now, the game we're going to play, you
and I, is that every single lesson that I
teach, I'm going to try
and win you over to buy it.
It's only a couple of hundred dollars.
And the cool part of this is if I win,
you win, because if I get your money, you
get to make more money
when you implement what you do on the
course. All right.
Let's get into the first big trap
that everyone falls for.
A lot of you are going to waste a huge
amount of time in your first few years
being
succumbed into free rent. Now,
you need a gym. You need a facility.
I'm very fortunate that I have my own gym,
but I had to use a commercial facility
all the way up until 2018, and I
was already making millions online
before getting this. And by the way,
this looks like a gym.
It's actually a content studio. Now,
the way you're going to think
is you're going
to think a place like this would be
amazing.
Oh, I could film content,
work with clients.
But commercial gyms
are just going to give you so many more
opportunities because
they've got a department
that work tirelessly around the clock
running marketing
campaigns to get people in the door.
And out of those people
that come through the door,
maybe only a few percent of
them be interested in personal training.
But that means you've got someone else
working for you to get prospects to come
in
the door.
For the majority of you watching this,
I think you should work in a
commercial facility
or at least a facility
that someone else around the clock is
going to try and get people to come
through the door so you can approach them,
you
can talk to them,
you can go up to them and say, "Hey." Not,
"Do you want some
personal training?"
But you can just be the helpful person on
the gym floor.
"Hey, mate, how's it going? I'm James.
I'm one of the PTs here.
I'm not here to interrupt your workout
or try and get you to sell PT.
Just letting you know, if there
is anything you need help with,
you let me know."
One of the first things
that people misinterpret with this kind of
approach on the
gym floor is even if there's a rugby
player there who's 6'2", benching 100
kg,
and probably never going to buy my
services, I just want to approach him and
let him know that I'm a decent person
because he might have a sister, a mum, an
auntie, someone that goes, "Oh,
I really want to start the gym,
but I need a PT."
And they'll go,
"There's a very switched on young man in
there that I saw the other
day that I spoke to.
I think he'd be perfect for you." Now,
the two models in
which gym rent goes: free and pay rent.
Now, free might seem like the better idea,
but it's not, and I'll explain why.
Nothing in life comes for free.
And often when people are saying
that you can have
free rent, some gyms, like PureGym,
say that you can do hours for the gym in
return. That's not free. Now,
some of them say 12 hours per week.
But the sneaky thing they do
is they then say,
"You can save X per month." So
let's say that the national average
is £400 a month for gym rent.
So if you're doing 12 hours per week to
save yourself £100, when you look at
it, it's not great money
that you're getting paid.
So there is no such thing as free rent.
Now, another way that people do it
is they're going to limit or cap your per
hour session, which means that
if you're doing under 20 hours,
you could be
financially better off. But
if you're doing over 20 hours,
it's probably going to
cost you more. Now,
one of the big issues
that I have with doing the free rent
model is when it comes to tax.
So let's do some really simple math for a
second. If you're a new personal trainer,
let's say you're charging £30 an hour.
If you do 30 sessions a week,
you're going to make £900.
That means in a month, 3,200. Now,
if your gym was to deduct
£400, you're still left with £2,800.
Now, my first gripe is that if you
are doing 12 hours a week for the gym,
it's going to be incredibly difficult to
do 30 sessions yourself.
The second thing is,
when you look at this as a percentage of
the revenue, it's not
a huge amount. But even
if you're somewhere that's more expensive
and it's £800 a
month,
you're still going to be left with 2,400 a
month.
Now, the issue here is
that a lot of people succumb to something
called loss
aversion.
And the way I can explain this to you
is if you worked for me as a sales
consultant and your on-target earnings
were 40K commission a year,
and I said to you, "What I'm going to do,
Dave or Fiona, I'm going to give you that
40,000 pounds or dollars right now,
and at the end of the year,
if you haven't hit
the target,
you've got to pay back to me what you
didn't earn," that would hurt you
a lot more,
and it'd probably get you to work quite
harder on the way to hitting
your on-target earning commission.
The psychological pain of losing money
always feels worse.
Another example would be
if we're walking down the street
and you drop a tenner,
you lose £10 or $10,
you're probably about this annoyed.
But if you were to find £10 or $10,
you're only about that happy.
The psychological pain of losing money
always feels worse than gaining it.
So people will do whatever they can to
avoid a loss, and they see the rental as a
loss.
But that's not the way to think about it.
If we do free on the left
and paid on the right,
and this isn't tax advice, if
you're doing free rent
and you're having to work for the gym,
you're ultimately
going to have less time,
you're going to earn less money.
So let's say on this side,
you earn 2,000 pounds plus free rent,
and on
this side you earn 3,200 minus, let's say,
800, just to make the figures
right. So some of you
are going to be standing there thinking,
"Hold on a second.
There's not a huge deal between it,
because on this side, you're making 2,400.
On this side you're making 2,000." The
benefit comes when running your own
business. This is a cost, and that cost
is a tax deductible.
You only pay tax on profits. Now,
working for free
is not a cost that you can deduct.
You can't go to HMRC or the ATO,
go, "Oh, but I worked for free.
Can I pay less tax?" They're going to go,
"No." And
a lot of the time, people
that work for free,
the gym sets stringent rules and
examples as to why they have to work
certain hours or they have to charge
certain
amounts. They have a lot of control.
Whereas the cost
that you pay for the gym
is a tax deductible.
So the tax office will look at the amount
of money you made, then it will deduct
your legitimate expenses, and the rent
is a legitimate expense.
And it can seem expensive,
but think about it.
All the equipment in the gym is very,
very expensive.
The building that you've got is very,
The air con,
even making sure there's toilet paper in
the bloody toilets, the
staff that are getting new members in
there.
When you break it down, this
is a sensible cost to the
business. And even
if you think 800 pounds a month is
expensive,
you couldn't hire someone on minimum wage
For that full time.
So it's something to consider.
Do you hire a member of staff
or do you pay
a gym to give you full autonomy to do
whatever you want in the facility?
You can come in when you want.
You can leave when you want.
You don't have to wipe down any machines.
You don't have to do any other thing for
the gym.
You can work completely for yourself
and the money that you
are spending at the end
of the year gets deducted from your
profitability, as does the camera,
the MacBook
Pro and the fitness expo
that you travel to.
It is always a better idea to take all of
the cash and have legitimate
deductions than it
is to give up your time so you can have
something for
free.
I'm at a stage in my career where my time
is worth so much
that if someone wanted to pay me $1,000
or £1,000 for an hour's phone call,
I'd say no,
and not because I'm a dickhead.
But in that one hour I could make this
video, which is going to sell me probably
15 to 30 PT starter kits,
and that's going to make me more than
1,000.
See where I'm going with this?
The next lesson that most of you need
is that you
need to start building your email list.
I remember listening to a podcast in 2014
where someone on there was asked his
biggest regret and the guy said,
"I wish I started an email list sooner."
It's
like, what the hell is that?
Think of it this way,
if you wanted to communicate
with a few hundred people right now to
send them a sensible offer,
how would you do
it? Would you go to Instagram Stories?
Would you create a reel?
And ultimately the issue is if you try
and do it on social media, that no one's
really going to care because there's only
a small percentage of audience that care
about your offer at any given point.
An email list is building a database of
people that are very interested in what it
is that you're selling. And
if you haven't started,
you already should.
If you've got one
and you're not utilizing it,
you really should.
No matter where you
are in your business and your life,
there is a point coming up
where you're going to send an email that's
going to make you $10,000.
It could take a few weeks,
could take a few months,
it could take a few years, but
ultimately you need to work your way
towards it.
And now you guys all know about
progressive overload.
So you start with one email subscriber,
then 10, then 100, and you never judge
someone on the gym about how weak they
are.
You just say, let's mark where you
are strength wise, and then let's seek
progressions from there on in.
Progressive overload works exactly same
with an
email list. The thing is,
if you're allocating four hours a week to
sales calls,
you know I don't like them, but anyway,
let's just say that you are.
You're not compounding that.
You can only do four sales calls in those
four hours
each week,
and in a year's time it's still four
hours, four sales calls.
Whereas if you spend
that time instead building content
or lead magnets to build an
email list,
you might have 100 subscribers now,
2,000 in six months,
11,000 in a year, 45,000 in two years.
And now you'd be in a position like me
where I've got over 400,000 email
subscribers, which is great for Nu Tonic,
it's great for this, it's great for
everything.
So if you haven't started an email list,
100% do it.
I've actually got another course on email
marketing that I believe is in the PT
starter kit, Inagi.
The next lesson would be
that so many personal trainers at the
moment are obsessed with what other
personal trainers are doing.
It's where they're going for market
research.
And the issue is
that most personal trainers
and online coaches don't actually
make that money or do that well.
So you're looking in the wrong place.
If you want to know what content you
should be making, you should be looking at
your clients, not other personal trainers.
Then the way in
which you make content must be different
and unique.
And the best way to do that
is to be yourself, because there
is only one version of
you and you're going to have something
called an idiosyncrasy.
And we can look at people, Adam Sullivan,
Sean Casey, Darren Cartel.
They all have a very unique way of
communicating and that unique way
is by being
themselves.
If you want to be unique in content,
don't copy the same thing that
every other personal trainer
is doing because every other personal
trainer is
broke. You need to be unique.
You need to trial test, do new things,
because
although it's a very saturated industry,
I don't believe it's that competitive.
Now, if there's one thing that I hate
that a lot of people do is that they don't
put their pricing on their website,
they want to build some kind of mystique
or
there's something mysterious
or let's get on a call and talk about it.
This is just shady ways of dealing with
people.
For instance, if I said, "Hey,
there's a hotel in Dubai,
really think you should go
to it." Go, "Cool, how much
is it a night?" It's probably going to be
the first
thing because you're shopping on a budget,
right?
You want to stay in the nicest place
possible,
but it's got to correlate with what
you can afford. And I said, "Oh,
the thing is, mate,
you've actually got to wait
till you get there for them to tell you."
You wouldn't do it.
If restaurants weren't transparent with
their pricing or what was on offer.
Because a website and a landing page
is really a menu for
what it is you're going to get.
And one of the key deciding principles in
whether
or not you make a purchase
or even visit in the first place
is the price.
And I've got an example for you.
I built this amazing shower outside my
house.
Copper taps, beautiful thing,
red hot water.
I shower outside at the moment,
actually quite crazy.
In my period in life I shower outside all
the time.
So in the morning I go get my toothbrush
and I brush my teeth outside.
Now my neighbors saw it like,
that's amazing.
And they said, "Oh, how much
was it?" Now at the time I didn't know
because Jamie,
the guy who came and fitted it,
I just told him to do it
and I didn't really ask
him how much it was.
I'm at a stage in my life where I don't
really care and that's
a bit of a flex.
Have I got a million pound in my bank
account? No.
But do I need to worry about the cost of a
shower? Also no.
So I said, "Look,
let me give you Jamie's number."
And my neighbors went, "Whoa,
whoa, whoa.
We don't want to waste anyone's time.
We're not interested." Cool.
Day later I get an invoice from Jamie.
It was, let's say $4,000.
I then go to my neighbors and I say, "Oh,
by the way, the shower was $4,000." They
go, "Give us his number.
We want one as well." They've now got a
matching shower
outside their house that's exact same as
mine.
And the point I'm trying to make there
is the wants were the same, the needs were
the same, the interest was the same.
The thing that determined whether
or not they bought was the price.
And it's not because they
were shopping on price.
They weren't looking for something cheap
or they wouldn't have spent $4,000 or
$5,000 on a shower. They wanted
that as an informed part
of making a decision of whether
or not they were going to go ahead
and make the
purchase. Show your pricing.
Be proud of your pricing, because
if you're expensive,
that only benefits you.
Think Apple give a shit they're more
expensive than anyone
else? No, it's premium pricing.
And let me give you another example.
This here is a cheap iPhone cable charger
and I'm pretty sure
it's broken and stopped working.
Now imagine this morning I wake up,
my alarm
doesn't go off. I'm late to work.
I've slept in,
which I'll never do with a child.
And it's because I bought a shitty iPhone
cable.
But I go to Amazon and I take a look
and there are three different cables on
show.
One of them is $6, one of them $7
and one of them is $19.99.
Considering that that cable
is so important to me
and I never want to be let down
and I don't want to have a fucking phone
run out of battery on me again, I'm going
to pick the £19.99 one. And
is it because I've become an expert in
USB-C
cables? No,
it's probably the best because it's the
most expensive.
So next time you think the pricing
is a negative gear towards what it
is you're
trying to do, it's just not true.
People like expensive things.
It's just a part of the decision process
they need to make.
Hiding your prices increases something
called a bounce rate
and most of you aren't
collecting the data from people
that bounce.
And what that means is
if someone gets to your site
and they can't see the price
and they don't click through to the link,
you don't know why they left.
And I'm telling you why a lot of people
leave.
No one's ever gone, "Oh my God,
I found this amazing coach.
I don't know how much they charge,
but I really want to buy their stuff." You
understand what I'm saying?
Just before I tell you about the next
thing, I wanted
you to know that if you go to the link in
the description and you buy anything from
me, whether it's the PT starter kit,
whether it's the email course, or even
if it's
my fully fledged business mentorship,
which I'm running a six-month cohort on,
where we're going to sprint between now
and the end of the year and I'm going to
get you online and I'm going to guarantee
you're making an extra 2K a month.
If you don't hit any of those,
I will refund you in full.
Which brings me on to the next point,
a money back guarantee.
How did that make you feel? Right there,
right now I'm saying to you, "Hey, I have
the knowledge, the expertise, the course,
everything that you need.
If you click on the links in the
description,
you'll see other people getting the
same results." But there stands a bit of a
risk that you need to take to trust me
and what I've done by giving you
that guarantee is I've taken away all of
that risk
where you're either going to get the thing
that you want or you're going to get
your money back. There's zero cost.
There's the risk
that you have on your shoulders as a
consumer, someone that I want
to purchase my stuff. I'm taking
that risk and I'm putting it on my
shoulders.
And if I'm honest, you might think
that I'm doing that for you, which I am,
but I'm
mostly doing it for me. You see,
my ability to sell improves when I give a
guarantee because it gives me confidence.
I can say to you, this
is going to help you,
because I know deep down if it
doesn't,
because you could be one of the few
percent that it doesn't, that you're
not going to have any bad feelings,
we're not going to have any bad blood,
you're
just going to get your money back
and a refund.
And I know the other thing as well
is me by doing that and saying
that to you, I'm
going to increase the sales fold on this
by maybe three or four times.
If you can make triple the sales with a 5%
to 10% refund rate, it's a pretty good
deal. It's a very good deal. And
if your refund rate's over 10%,
you probably need
to change what you're doing with your
product and your offering and get some
feedback from people because something
there just isn't going as it should.
That money back guarantee information
that I gave you on its own is a massive
leverage play for you to make more sales
online.
You know I said at the beginning we're
going to play a game whether
or not you buy
my stuff? That should have solidified it,
but we'll keep going because there's
quite a few more golden nuggets
that you need.
You must commit to being an in-person
coach.
And I know it's not sexy
and I know long days in the gym suck,
but I earn really,
really good money now. Right now
that camera is sat on my Porsche 911 GT3.
But I used to work for £20 an hour
and even though those days in that
gym in Bracknell can seem underwhelming,
it was there that I learnt the
craft It was there
that I got to really understand people,
their
needs, their wants,
and every conversation
that I had with them.
When I programmed online,
I knew what the people were,
I knew what they were after,
I knew the issues they were having.
When they got to a bottom of a squat
and they were having an issue,
I knew exactly
how to identify it. Think about this,
Matt Armstrong, arguably my favorite
YouTuber, he rebuilds crash-damaged cars.
The reason I've got a 911 GT3
is because of that pleb,
because he made me fall in
love with the car and now I have it.
He didn't learn to become a mechanic
whilst
on YouTube.
He spent years before he ever turned a
camera on when he was BMX-ing,
learning all the intricacies of how cars
operate.
We could argue that Matt Armstrong had
more time and hours
unpaid or very poorly paid.
Now he's a multi-multi-millionaire.
There is a lesson in
that for people to understand.
These hours that suck on the gym floor,
the long days, the learning people, it is
that that made me good online.
Someone said to me the other day,
"You're good at
communicating." I said,
"Thank you." Seven hours a day with
clients, talking
nonstop. Then let's not forget,
when I wasn't doing paid hours
of PT or I had a cancellation, I
was then engaging in sales.
"Hey, Janice. How's it going?
How's stuff going? Yeah. Great. Cool.
You remember you have got
that free program.
If you want to come in for a trial,
you can do it on Tuesday." "Hey, John.
You got new trainers. Love to see you,
man.
Let me know if you're ever going to want
to do 10-pack again." It is nonstop
communication. Everything
that I have now comes from the jobs
that sucked before.
Now, PT as a job does suck a bit,
but as you all should know by now,
I come from
background [chuckles] door-to-door sales,
I come from background of being in a call
center,
I come from backgrounds of really shitty
jobs.
Getting paid 30,
40 pounds an hour to chat to someone in a
nice air-conditioned
gym, and the fact
that you can train yourself between a
cancellation, it's not
really as bad as people are making out.
In person isn't sexy.
It will suck for a long time,
but the riches you're going to get in five
years come
from the suck that you're going to get in
the one year from here on in.
You need to trust me on that. Time
and content live in this very interesting
continuum, and I'll explain.
Because right now, today, typically,
I'd be
training Brazilian jujitsu,
but I have a hospital appointment with my
fiancée.
I'm not going to get into too much detail.
So I've now been given
that amount of time back.
That extra hour for me has permitted me to
make this video.
Which is another reason
that I'm not a big fan of sales calls
because like I said,
the compounding effect of putting time
into things, you give me an hour, I'm
creating a banger YouTube video that's
going to make me thousands of dollars and
sell loads of PT starter kit
and probably get a few people into the
business
account.
Not to mention at the end of this video,
even if people aren't interested
and buy stuff,
I get to point them at an end card to go
to another video.
And this video sits on the internet
forever.
YouTube is going to work around the clock
trying to find people that are perfect
for this video and continue bringing
people to it.
A year from now,
someone's going to watch this video
and look and go, "Wow, this
was recorded a year ago,
but YouTube still put it in front of me."
There is an
employee in the world that works for free.
Their name is YouTube.
They work 24 hours, seven days a week.
And guess what?
There's other employees called Instagram
and TikTok and Facebook, and they're all
there just wanting to take the video
that you made today and put it in front of
people so that they're interested in
buying your stuff.
Do you know how amazing that is?
And you want to be on the phone with
someone for
an hour so they can make a decision
whether or not they buy your stuff.
That's why I'm saying that's fucking
stupid. Make content instead.
Make content instead.
I want you to be a well-paid coach.
I want you to make really good money.
I want you to charge loads by the hour.
But in the onset,
you just don't have the right.
When I started my business, Mentorship,
it was a fraction of the cost it was now
because I had two choices.
Do I launch something that no one buys
and it bombs, or
do I launch something that's underpriced,
and as I build demand, I make it better?
Because in the early stages,
letting people in for cheap meant I got to
learn them,
they got to learn me,
I got to use their results,
they got to tap in and get things
underpriced from me. I
was doing one-to-one calls for $500 an
hour.
It was way better for me to start cheap
and work up and titrate up.
The exact same thing as progressive
overload.
We want to start with something
that we can handle now
and do quite easily, and
it's better that a workout
is too easy than too difficult.
It is better that the weight
is too light than too heavy.
It is better that we start with volume in
an accumulation phase than we progress to
intensity.
These are all the principles
that we know from training, yet we
don't always apply it to our business.
So how much should you charge?
Start cheap, get full, and the second
that you hit full capacity, increase
prices. That is the commodity that
is used in everything, even aviation on
planes. The thing
that determines how expensive a plane seat
is isn't where it's
going, it's how many people want
that seat.
And most airlines with a low capacity full
on an
aircraft will reduce prices to get bums on
seats.
The more bums on seats,
the more they're going to increase prices.
This is the world of commodity and demand,
and I think it's really important that
for all of you, you just swallow your ego,
start cheap, build up.
It's the best way to do it. Now,
I wish someone had told me this a little
bit
sooner when it comes to having annoying
clients.
Should there be enough demand for your
services, you get to a point where you can
sack clients. Now,
there's an 80/20 principle,
it's called Pareto's law, I believe,
where everything's split into 80/20.
Can we get some real examples of this?
Because I actually don't know any off of
my top.
Pareto's law, give me some examples.
That's pretty much what I use AI for these
days.
80% of outcomes come from 20% of causes.
Top 20% of earners have 80% of the wealth.
Top 20% of bugs cause 80% of crashes.
Whatever it is, but basically,
20% of your clients
are going to cause 80% of your
headaches. So for many of you,
you have the opportunity where
if you sack two
clients,
you could end up with 20% less money for
100% less
headaches. And that to me
is a really good deal.
There's also something that happens
when you sack someone.
It's a bit of a power move.
Most personal trainers would rather live
in misery and
have four sessions that they hate
and do not want to do.
And I've had them,
and I wish I had the courage to sack them
sooner.
But when you say to a client, "Hey,
this isn't working,"
and you refund the money,
it empowers you,
and you should do anything within your
power to empower yourself.
And getting rid of clients that
are shitty also sends a shockwave through
the gym
because someone's going to go, "Oh,
I thought you were training with James."
"Oh,
he sacked me." "What?" "Yeah, he said
that I wasn't getting the results
and it was
making him look bad,
so he sent me on my way."
That wasn't the real reason.
She was a bit of a cunt. So that's it.
At the end of the day,
you have the power to sack clients,
and the more you do it,
the better you'll feel about it,
and I just wish someone had told me sooner
how
fucking bloody amazing it feels to sack
clients and let them go.
There is some advice
that I really disagree with.
For online, for instance,
the majority of people think you should
sell in DMs, and
I think that if you're going to utilize
DMs, they should be automated, and if
they're not automated,
you just get a member of staff to send
people to a landing
page. Because at the end of the day,
say you needed a surgeon to repair your
ACL. You don't want
that surgeon to be in the DMs, "Oh,
please, come in.
Let's book you in on the second. Oh,
I'd love to see you." Most good surgeons
are
like, "Yeah, I can see you in four months.
Do you want the appointment? Yes or no?
It's $10,000." Well, don't bother.
The people that are truly great at what
they do, they're not spending-...
their spare time in DMs. Actually,
if anyone's got a brain,
remember what we spoke
about before. If you've got spare time,
spend it making content, because any good
video can drastically change the state of
your life.
I've had a video on TikTok
that got me 1 million followers.
So when it comes to spending time
and energy and effort into DMs,
there's two
problems here. One is
that you're not spending time in a place
that can compound
and reward you.
But the second thing as well is,
if you spend 10, 15, 20 minutes
trying to close someone in the DMs,
and they say,
"No" you've got to carry that
weight with you all the time.
It's another reason I don't like sales
calls, because
I'm actually quite insecure,
and I really don't like it
when I get feedback on
something failing. So for instance,
if this video gets 10,000 views and
9,100 people don't even click through to
the landing page, that's fine.
I don't know about that.
I don't lay in bed tonight thinking about
it.
But if at the same merit,
I did a sales call today in 45 minutes,
and I'm getting
on with Susan amazing,
she's perfect for the program.
I then pitch, and then get to the end,
and she goes, "I need to think about it."
And then she never gets back to me
and doesn't respond to my emails
and never gets
back to any of the phone calls.
Then I start to think about Susan all the
time, and
I'm laying there in bed just thinking
about Susan, thinking,
"Where did I go wrong?
And why am I not good enough to be
accepted by people?" Which
is another reason
why don't think you should spend time in
DMs.
If there's anything you should do,
you should be putting time and energy
and effort
into things that compound.
Even this video.
You'll notice this
is a slightly different video to usual.
The way that I'm listing off,
we're going for scene changes
and visual hooks, and
I'm currently using the DJI Pocket Osmo 4
to note whether or not the
quality of this camera is noticeable.
I'm not filming in log either,
filming in auto,
and I want to see how that impacts
into my retention. Because even
if no one buys from this video,
it's not a failure,
it's a perfect opportunity for me to try
something and see whether or not it works
better, worse, or the same as other means
in which we're doing. And actually,
if I'm completely honest, I'm also testing
Ollie. He's my YouTube strategist.
You get access to him in the mentorship,
by the way.
So when you join, it's not just me,
it's Cam, my marketing right-hand man.
You've also got Ollie. Ollie told me
that these would be the best talking
points to
talk about.
I'm actually going to chip him in on every
sale of this video.
So Ollie's learning, I'm learning.
Ollie and I will test some titles
and thumbnails, and the better Ollie gets,
the
better I do. But the better I do,
the better Ollie earns.
And this is a way for me
and Ollie to both find out what our
audience wants and
needs. So we're also testing this.
A few thousand dollars from this video
won't be life-changing,
but the information
that we learn from it probably will.
Which brings me on to another point that's
not in his notes.
You'll notice that in this video,
I didn't plan or prepare a thing.
I turned up to the gym with Ollie's
talking points because the knowledge I
have is
already here. I can't help but feel
that a lot of people online at the moment
are
just putting things into Claude,
reading them off a teleprompter.
It seems kind of robotic.
I'm here chatting to you like you're my
mate, but I'm
recording it. If my mate was here,
I'd say, "Look, what?
You want me to waste all my breath on just
you? Just you. You're only my friend.
You're only a pathetic piece of meat with
bones in it." Me, if I'm going to give
you advice after fucking decades of
working this shit out, I'm going to record
it, so at least I can get paid from it.
That's why I've got no friends.
I haven't socialized with friends in ages.
I mean, I've got them,
but more like group chat mates.
The issue is, and it sounds bad,
they're poor.
So let's say I go hang with them.
Where am I parking, the 911? Fuck,
I can't.
They live in apartments.
They haven't got spare parking spaces.
They live in, like, a two-bed.
And, I'm like,
"Let's spend a couple grand this weekend."
And they go, "Oh, I'm
saving." What's that? Yeah, so, this
is actually probably, if you want to be
successful,
don't get too successful because,
Thursday afternoon, there I am
driving my Porsche around a track,
and I'm like,
I'm with all these old people.
People go,
"Why not invite your friends?" They're at
work.
And that's the curse of being one of the
most successful online personal trainers
ever to do this. You have friends,
not many, but they're poor. Yeah.
Be a nice problem to have, though,
wouldn't it? I'm only fucking with you.
[laughs] I've had so many mates over the
years that have become personal trainers,
and they've got no clients,
and they've not looked at the fact they've
got shit
marketing. Instead, they go,
"I need to do an S&C degree," or, "I
need to do an MBA." And I'm like, mate,
qualifications.
Obviously, if you're a surgeon,
get your qualifications.
You're a doctor, do your qualification.
If you're a pilot, do your qualification.
But as a personal trainer, honestly,
nothing beats raw experience.
You can do some courses, but even
if you were going to go do, like, a glute
training course with someone,
I'd do it just for the fact so you can
then shout
about it on social media and go, "Hey,
look at me, I'm a personal trainer.
I'm doing personal development." Yeah,
like, even looking back, I went to
uni, and I didn't go to any lectures.
And on my CV, I put a 2.2.
Then it became a 2.1. Before you knew it,
I had a first in exercise
sport science,
which I didn't even study that, honestly.
So,
don't worry too much about qualifications.
You want your level three PT so you can
get insured on the gym floor, but after
that, it doesn't really matter that much.
I've lied about most of my qualifications.
I am probably the most underqualified
person that you watch on YouTube.
Yeah. What are they going to do?
Call the cops?
"Oh, James lied about having a first
or a 2.1." Is that illegal?
Is that illegal? Is that illegal?
One thing that's kind of controversial
that I say
to a lot of people
is you should niche down to a problem,
not a person.
So for instance, if you are,
"I help shift workers
lose fat," you're niching down to a type
of person.
Now, shift workers, it's cool.
I think it's valiant
that you're going after that as
a niche. But I don't know
if I fully agree with that,
because shift workers, the
problem is they're sleep deprived,
poor circadian rhythm, yappa, yappa,
yappa.
But then you could also work with parents
with newborns because they'd be facing
the exact same issue, right? So
if you were to niche to a problem instead
of a
person, you could be like,
"If for whatever reason your sleep
is not to scratch,
here's some tactics and protocols
that you can use to fix it.
I've created this lead magnet for people
that aren't getting eight hours of sleep a
night." Because then a parent could
download it,
a shift worker could download it,
a fucking air stewardess could download
it.
I think it's really important
that you niche to a problem, not a person,
because there are more people with the
problem than there are the people that
you're aiming for.
If you're a gay man trying to lose weight,
that is trying to
niche to a person, and I think that
is terrible.
And also,
I don't understand why a gay person would
have
caloric differences.
Let's not get into it. Dirty buggers.
Another thing to think about is
that you are the brand,
not your business name.
So some people are crippled by the fact
that they need to be called Active Health
PT, or Better For You, or Strong For Life.
No one is paying Strong For Life.
No one is paying Active Health PT.
They're paying you.
You are Tricia, or you're Jordan,
or you're Dave.
I was JS Training, and then I realized,
and then I had, like, the little gay
icon and stuff. Can you say that? Did.
And then from that, I
was like JS Training, fat loss educator.
Then I was like, do you know what?
I'm James Smith. Then I had to put PT.
Then in the end,
I had to pay someone to get the handle
James Smith because the
fucker that had the James Smith handle
was a PT andAnd I was like, "Give it up,
mate. Give it up." Because you know what?
If you're an actor
and your name's Leonardo DiCaprio
and you're not Leonardo
DiCaprio, then just give it up, mate.
You know what I mean? It's not happening.
It's too late. It's over. You're too old.
Let go. It's over.
Nobody listens to techno. So you
are the brand. You are the representative.
Whatever you've got there,
just change it to your name.
And it might seem like you have to
unattach yourself,
but what you don't want is
someone to see you in the street and go,
"Oh, it's the fitness chef." "What's his
name?" "Don't know." It's Graham,
and Graham is a person, and he has a name.
Represent your brand.
Stand up for your brand.
When someone wants a selfie,
you don't want them to say you're the guy
from
Facebook, which I've been called before.
Long story short, I
was on a night out with Sam Burgess
and Ant Middleton, probably
the best night of my life.
Not President Middleton, Sam Burgess.
You know what I mean? If you know,
you know.
And as we walk in, someone's like,
"Oh my God,
that's Ant Middleton from 'SAS: Who
Dares Wins.' Oh, my God." Then, "Oh,
Sam Burgess.
Oh my God, you're the fucking man,
Sam Burgess." Then I walk,
then you're the guy
from Facebook. Still not lived that down.
We're going to fast-fire the last few
rounds.
Look, it's not the algorithms,
it's not the social media platform,
it's not the
world against you, it's that you
are just not good enough at content yet.
You are probably 500 to 600 repetitions
away from getting
good. Cadence, speaking tone, hooks,
repetition, volume is key.
There's that analogy about making pots.
If you get two groups of people
and one group has to make a perfect pot
and they've
got a month to make it,
then the other group has a month to make
as many pots as
possible, chances are the perfect pot
is going to come from the group of people
making as many pots as possible,
because the volume and the repetitions.
So let's not forget that.
Time needs to be spent not just working in
the business.
So for instance, today,
I can work in the business in the Discord
helping people
out,
but I need to work on the business by
making these videos to set things up and
assets that go on the internet. When I
was personal training, I would spend six
hours personal training people in person
in the gym, but then I would spend at
least an hour and a half in Waitrose
working on the business.
In the business is earning things to put
money in my pocket now.
On the business is creating things for
free that in the future will pay me.
Like this video.
No one's paying me to make this video,
but in the future, this
video will pay me. It is important
that you segment your time into not just
doing
things in the business,
but on the business too.
And when you are sat there in Waitrose
Cafe, right, stop posting about your
workouts. No one cares.
Don't post about what you had for lunch.
No one cares.
Don't post about your dog. Actually, no,
sometimes dogs and cats.
Cats work very well in hooks. But yeah,
ultimately, every single piece of content
you make is about them. Even
if you've had a win,
if you've lost 10 kilograms,
don't say,
"This is how I lost 10 kilograms." You
say, "If you want to lose 10
kilograms, here's a strategy
that you can use because I just did it
and it worked,
and it was easier than I could ever have
expected, and I don't think you're going
to believe how easy it
is until you try it." Everything you post
about is about
them. Even if it's about you,
it's about them. Do you understand?
I'm telling you information about my life,
but I'm positioning it in a way where it
benefits you and you only.
And the last thing
is what separates personal trainers,
the ones that make it and those
that don't?
And to be honest,
you've got to be a bit of a fucking geek.
And I'm not saying
that you have to buy my course
or study under me, but I studied
under loads of people.
I studied under Mark Coles,
under Phil Learney, under Martin
MacDonald.
I geeked out every single opportunity I
could.
I bought several YouTube courses.
I'm always investing in development.
And the crazy thing is,
the amount of money
that I put into personal development
from people, I always 10, 20X, 30X
or whatever.
Even Ed Lawrence, my YouTube sensei,
who I'm always-- The reason I give so
much love to Ed,
not because he's given us hundreds of
thousands of dollars of
investment into Neotonic, which was nice.
The main thing is Ed
is single-handedly responsible for not
just
teaching me, but inspiring me.
He laid out a path of growing on
YouTube,
and it inspired me to do it myself,
and it's made me nearly $6
million in just over two years.
I intend to do the same thing for you as a
personal
trainer. And if not me,
make it someone that you respect their
journey, you
admire what they've done,
and you will listen to what they teach
you.
I truly believe that every single one of
the things that I offer has a massive
return on investment if you do it right.
And if you are an online fitness coach
and you've watched through all of this and
you're not considering buying my stuff,
then fuck you.
But also fuck you, and there
is a video here that YouTube recommends
that if you
watch this,
you will continue your little course of
learning and you'll turn into a
smart little boffin. And if you watch
that one, you will do very well.
But don't even worry about that one
that much and just buy the fucking thing
that
I'm telling you to buy.
I've got mouths to feed.
Hope you enjoyed the video.